Finding Aid for Jens Jensen Drawings and Papers 1903-1951
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Drawings
  - Y-Z
    - Younker, A., Winnetka, Illinois
      - Plan of topo. survey. Estate of Mr. A. Younker., 1911; YOU1; Pencil, ink on linen; topo. lines, elevations, location of residence; signed; 117 x 37 cm.; Scale: 1"" = 20' (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - Estate of Mr. A. Younker...Plan of topo. survey., 1913; YOU2; Pencil, ink on linen; topo. lines, elevations, residence, proposed (?) driveway, walks and garage; residence by A.S. Alschuler; signed (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - Planting plan. Estate. Mr. A. Younker., 1913; YOU3; Ink on linen; location, type, amounts of plantings; gardens; residence by A.S. Alschuler; penciled notes; signed; 101 x 33 cm.; Scale: 1"" = 20' (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
    - Zimmerman, H.B., Oenera, Illinois
      - Plat of survey..., 1921; ZIM1; Blueprint; dimensions of property; original unsigned; 56 x 59 cm.; No scale (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - A plat of topo. survey for the property of Mr. H.B. Zimmerman., 1921; ZIM2; Ink on linen; location of residence, driveway, trees, gardens; unsigned; 132 x 62 cm.; Scale: 1"" = 20' (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - A plat of topo. survey for the property of Mr. H.B. Zimmerman., 1921; ZIM3; Blueprint; print of ZIM2; revisions in pencil and yellow and white crayon; original unsigned; 133 x 61 cm.; Scale: 1"" = 20' (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - A planting plan for a portion of the estate of Mr. H.P. [sic] Zimmerman., 1922; ZIM4; Ink on linen; location, type, amount of plantings; signed; 100 x 28 cm.; Scale: 1"" = 20' (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - A planting plan for the garden areas. Estate of Mr. H.P. [sic] Zimmerman., 1924; ZIM5; Ink on linen; location, type, amounts of plantings; list of planting types, sizes, quantities; signed; 88 x 28 cm. (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
      - A planting plan for a portion of the estate of Mr. H.B. Zimmerman., 1927; ZIM6; Ink on linen; location, type, amounts of plantings; footpaths, seats; unsigned; 69 x 56 cm.; Scale: 1"" = 20' (Map-case 60, Folder 92)
- Manuscript Material
  The Manuscripts Series (ca. 1920-1960; .5 linear ft.), while limited in extent and scope, is particularly valuable because it is the only source of information in the collection beyond the visual. The series includes background material collected by Leonard Eaton, Eaton's handwritten notes, Jensen correspondence with clients, letters written on behalf of Friends of Our Native Landscape, and items Jensen mailed to the editors of various newspapers. (Unfortunately, much of the client communication was photocopied from fading thermofax and is difficult to read.) The series also includes a few lecture notes, a handful of published material both by and about Jensen, and a typescript of the Chicago Tribune obituary of October 2, 1951.
  - Background (collected by Leonard Eaton) (Box 1)
    - General, 1959-1963; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Chicago Parks Publications, 1897; 1918 (Box 1)
    - Century of Progress, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Clearing, The, 1944-1959 (Box 1)
    - Early Years, Denmark (photographs), undated (Box 1)
    - Frank Lloyd Wright (includes 3 Taliesin photographs), 1932; undated (Box 1)
    - Obituary, Chicago Tribune, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    (mainly thermofax and photocopies of thermofax)
    - General, 1934-1945; undated (Box 1)
    - Eichsteadt, E.A., 1926-1927; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Ford, Edsel, 1920-1934; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Friends of our Native Landscape, 1928-1940 (Box 1)
    - Knudson, Mrs. (Lincoln Garden), 1934-1938; undated (Box 1)
    - Letters to Editors, 1934-1942; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Longenecker, G. William, 1944-1949 (Box 1)
    - Seymour, Ralph Fletcher, 1939-194? (Box 1)
    - Translated from the Danish, 1936-1951 (Box 1)
  - Writings By and About
    - About Jensen (Box 1)
    - By Jensen
      - Articles, General, 1933-1944 (Box 1)
      - Lecture Notes, 1933-1934; undated (Box 1)
      - Letters to Editors
        - General, 1934-1942; 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Capital Times, Madison, Wisconsin, 1940-1943 (Box 1)
        - Chicago Daily News, 1940 (Box 1)
      - Friends of Our Native Landscape (Includes Proposed Park Areas in the State of Illinois: A Report with Recommendations and Yearbook for the Year MCMXIV), 1921-1940 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1913-1960
  The bulk of the Photographs (ca. 1913-1960; 1.5 linear ft.) series is a set of glass plate negatives of Midwestern native plants taken by Jensen and associated contact prints. (Prints were prepared by the Art and Architecture Library, University of Michigan, date unknown). The glass plates were removed from brittle and crumbling paper envelopes and placed in acid-free housing. Titles, place names, and date of exposure were transcribed from the envelopes. Because of the fragile nature of these negative images, researchers are asked to view the contact prints, rather than the original glass plates.
  There are also a number of photographs and negatives of Jensen designed parks and estates as they appeared in the mid 1950s and early 1960s (commissioned by Leonard Eaton). In some cases, Robert Fine is identified on the verso as the photographer; in other examples, the photographer is unknown. Very often these folders also contain 4 x 5 inch negatives. Occasionally the image is of a Jensen drawing rather than the developed property.
  The series also includes copy negatives of drawings that have been photographed. Researchers should consult the drawer listing of the finding aid to determine which drawings have copy negatives (example: neg: TIL 1)
  - Jensen, Jens (Box 1)
    (includes one Jensen portrait, and one image of Jensen "with two Danish visitors," 1946)
  - Parks and Other Public Work ( for Eaton book), circa 1950-1960
    - Chicago Parks (Box 1)
    - Humboldt Park, Chicago (Box 1)
    - Knickerbocker Blvd. and Hammond, Indiana (Box 1)
    - Lincoln Memorial Garden, Springfield, Illinois (includes photograph of Jensen and Mrs. Knudson) (Box 1)
    - Racine, Wisconsin (Box 1)
  - Clients / Private ( for Eaton book), circa 1950-1960
    - Aldrich, Frank; Bloomington, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Babson, Henry; Riverside, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Becker, A.G.; Highland Park, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Clarke, Harley; Evanston, Illinois (Box 1)
    - David, Sigmund; Glencoe, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Dell Plain, Morse; Hammond, Indiana (Box 1)
    - Ferriss, Edward; St. Charles, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Florsheim, Arnold; Highland Park, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Ford, Henry; Dearborn, Michigan (Box 1)
    - Gill, Wallace; Evanston, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Goodman (Box 1)
    - Keller, Oren; Rossford, Ohio (Box 1)
    - Kurth, Herbert; Mequon, Wisconsin (Box 1)
    - Northmoor County Club (Box 1)
    - Roberts, Abby; Marquette, Wisconsin (Box 1)
    - Rosenwald, Julius; Highland Park, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Rubens, Harry; Glencoe, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Ryerson, E.L.; Lake Forest, Illinois (Box 1)
    - Sieck, Herbert; Winnetka, Illinois (Box 1)
  - Copy Prints from Glass Plate Negatives
    - Flowering Dogwood: Baileytown, May 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (1)
    - False Solomon's Seal Detail, May 10, 1913 (Box 1)
      (2)
    - Columbine: Dune Park, May 10, 1913 (Box 1)
      (3)
    - Columbine Detail: Dune Park, May 10, 1913 (Box 1)
      (3a)
    - Willow Habit: Dune Park, May 10, 1913 (Box 1)
      (4)
    - Willow Detail: Dune Park, may 10 1913 (Box 1)
      (5)
    - Phlox: Mineral Springs, June 14, 1913 (Box 1)
      (6)
    - Phlox: Mineral Springs, May 18, 1913 (Box 1)
      (7)
    - Choke Cherry: Mineral Springs, May 18, 1913 (Box 1)
      (8)
    - Choke Cherry: Baileytown, May 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (9)
    - Star Flower: Mineral Springs, May 18, 1913 (Box 1)
      (10)
    - Lupine: Mineral Springs, May 18, 1913 (Box 1)
      (11)
    - Lupine: Dune Park, May 10, 1913 (Box 1)
      (12)
    - Tall Blueberry: Baileytown, May 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (13)
    - Tall Blueberry Detail: Baileytown, May 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (14)
    - Chokeberry: Mineral Springs, May 24, 1913 (Box 1)
      (15)
    - Chokeberry Detail: Furnessville, June 1, 1913 (Box 1)
      (16)
    - Hoary Pea: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (17)
    - Coreopsis: Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (18)
    - Butterfly Milkweed: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (19)
    - Puccoon Lithospermum: Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (20)
    - Cactus: Mineral Springs, July 6, 1913 (Box 1)
      (21)
    - Rosablanda: Dune Park, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (22)
    - Rosablanda: Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (23)
    - Rosahumilis: Dune Park, June 9, 1913 (Box 1)
      (24)
    - Osmunda Cinnamonia: Mineral Springs, May 24, 1913 (Box 1)
      (26)
    - Pink Lady's Slipper: Mineral Springs, May 30, 1913 (Box 1)
      (27)
    - Hudsonia: Mineral Springs, July 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (28)
    - Bluebell Campanula: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (31)
    - Helianthermum Cavadense (?): Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (32)
    - Dwarf Dogwood: Mineral Springs, May 24, 1913 (Box 1)
      (32a)
    - Hairbelt Liheria: Furnessville, June 1, 1913 (Box 1)
      (33)
    - Yellow Lady's Slipper: Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (34)
    - Yellow Lady's Slipper: Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (35)
    - Tradiscant Virginaca (?): Dune Park, June 8, 1913 (Box 1)
      (35a)
    - Calopsoqau (?): Mineral Springs, July 1913 (Box 1)
      (36)
    - Twin Flower: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (37)
    - Blackberry Detail: Furnessville, June 1, 1913 (Box 1)
      (38)
    - Brown-eyed Susan: Dune Park, July 6, 1913 (Box 1)
      (39)
    - White Water Lily: Dune Park, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (40)
    - False Indigo: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (41)
    - Tiger Lily: Dune Park, July 12., 1913 (Box 1)
      (42)
    - Showy Lady's Slipper: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (43)
    - Showy Lady's Slipper: Mineral Springs, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
      (44)
    - Swamp Rose: Mineral Springs, July 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (45)
    - Mondara Punetata:, July 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (46)
    - New Jersey Tea: Dune Park, July 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (47)
    - Osier Dogwood: Mineral Springs, July 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (48)
    - Pedicularis Canadensis: Dune Park, May 4, 1913 (Box 1)
      (49)
    - Star Grass Yellow: Dune Park, May 4, 1913 (Box 1)
      (50)
    - Cherry: Furnessville, May 4, 1913 (Box 1)
      (51)
    - Sand Cherry: Dune Park, May 4, 1913 (Box 1)
      (52)
    - Swamp Rose: Mineral Springs, July 17, 1913 (Box 1)
      (unnumbered)
    - White Water Lily: Dune Park, June 22, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Original Paper Sleeves for Glass Plate Negatives (Box 1)
  - Copy Negatives of Photographed Drawings (Box 1)
  - Unidentified Negatives (4 of "trees and opening") (Box 1)
  - Glass Plate Negatives (Box 2)
    (Items described above in copy prints of glass negatives)
    (Restricted: Staff use only)